okay welcome everybody thank you for
coming especially from Mexico you
so I had kind of an idea that I'd like
to tell you about a project that we're
working on that I think you don't know
about because I also forgot about it so
let's start with that because it relates
to the text that we're going to study
okay and then we'll go to the angel demo
okay
okay how do you connect me to the my
computer my computer yes okay again okay
so let's see
this is a project that jing-mei and I
have been working on for since I don't
know December of 2012 something good
about six years seven years and the idea
is that we would like to establish the
English names for the cumbia so the
conga is 1000 books spoken by the Buddha
and the biggest collection in the world
that survives by the by the Buddha is in
Tibet and socom means speech of the
Buddha gira means translated into
Tibetan from Sanskrit and then after
that India was attacked taken over by
the moguls who built the Taj Mahal for
example and that was like I don't know
five hundred years seven years then they
were taken over by the British who also
didn't much they weren't much interested
you don't have a charity come on
so there was a problem there's a chair
back there yeah so anyway the books were
lost and they only survived in Tibet we
have a we have a large team in South
India Kerala and in Varanasi and in
Katmandu who are looking for the
Sanskrit Christina Karthik is working on
gemelas working on that and I just been
doing great work on that and they
recovered just about all that we're
gonna recover and we have a new team in
Katmandu who's looking for the Sanskrit
texts in other scripts and they're
making good progress but basically the
only place you can get all of the
Buddhist books is in Tibetan recently
I've become very familiar with the
Chinese and I think only 75 books
started Chinese Buddhism okay Swensen in
the Tong dynasty Tong
about the time of Kamala Sheila walked
through India for 17 years and came home
with about 75 books in 900 fascicles so
then the tradition says he translated
900 books but I decided it was 75 books
in 900 fascicles and that's all of
Chinese Buddhism started from that and
and an earlier translation one
individual named commander Jeeva who did
the Heart Sutra in the diamond cutter
but so really it's Tibetan where you can
find a thousand of the remaining works
of the Buddha and then well I we decided
to standardize the names of the thousand
books because they're very confused no
one has ever named them in in English so
the names are there in Tibetan and the
Tibetans always put a Sanskrit name mr.
the Tibetan name at the top at the front
of the book for those thousand books so
we have the Sanskrit and we have the
Tibetan and then some of them have been
named by people who translated them and
we decided six years seven years ago we
would name all of them and so me and
Jigme started in coffee shops and it was
really fun and we just do it every time
we have time we go to this little coffee
shop
yeah which gets less and less in guest
iliza life and yeah 2018 here and we
won't talk about it right now
we didn't do it once I think yeah so
anyway and we do it every time we have
any time at all and we finished about a
third
we finished 400 titles and the problem
is you have to read the book to
translate the title so sometimes you
have to read 20-30 pages to to translate
the title and I put a couple of examples
in here for you Gondo view heart sutra
is very famous in the west and it's
traditionally translated as stocks of
stocks in array you know view ha means
like in a pattern
and in Gundam in stocks and has nothing
to do with that the book is about a
magic house surrounded by trees that are
all made of different jewels like one
tree of emerald and one tree of ruby and
it sings the Dharma it has nothing to do
with barley stocks you see I mean and
but that name has stuck and the Diamond
Sutra has stuck and we were in Japan two
weeks ago and they're all like what's
diamond cutter and I'm like you don't
know it's diamond cutter they're like Oh
Diamond Sutra I said it's not Diamond
citrus time budget Erica it's diamond
cutter Sutra you know and it's extremely
important that you call it the cutter
and like that so we basically figured
out that many many of the names have
been mistaken so we've been naming them
and we plan to finish by 2029 and we've
covered about thirty-four thousand pages
so far and we have now it would take
seven hundred years traditionally to
translate those books into Tibetan from
Sanskrit now then I put in a section on
how to speed up the work basically we
need more people which means we need
more money okay and it just it's a flat
formula more money more people we can
finish no more money no more people
cannot finish it's very wet econ
straightforward there's no debate about
it it's just how many people you have
you can finish okay we'd like to do the
pinger which is three times longer three
thousand two hundred fifty six works
it's two hundred and six thousand one
hundred and fifty pages okay and that
will take us I will be a hundred and
twenty-two when we finish
at this rate but I it's not a project
that we talk about and we've just been
quietly doing it for six or seven years
and I think we should give Jigme here
but it also involves fixing the Sanskrit
titles Christmas the Tibetans by then
didn't know Sanskrit so well and it's no
longer taught in Tibetan monasteries so
we have to fix the sounds good titles
though so we've been doing both then I
thought you guys you can appreciate
today's this weekend's talk better if
you understood the structure of the
cumbia you know what's left from Lord
Buddha okay so I thought I would tonight
I would talk about the structure of the
conger because our author has been
covering 26 lousy kinds of meditation 26
kinds of meditation that are slightly
defective and and subtly defective okay
so he's gonna cover 26 then he takes a
little break to whine about things and
then he goes off on the traditional
schools of Buddhism
starting with Siddhanta Siddhanta means
you traditionally start with the Hindu
schools that the Buddha came out of in
the way that Jesus came out of the
Jewish schools you see so traditionally
you cover the meditations of the Hindu
schools - - they're grouped into two
groups one doesn't believe in karma
doesn't believe in future lives
they're called nihilists and then there
is what you look better today you didn't
lift concrete socks all day
just dogs eternalists which which would
say there's a soul that the but that we
have a soul and different ideas about
eternal soul and then once you get
through that you start with the lower
Buddhist schools and you work up to the
lower Buddhist schools and then you
reach the high school and our author the
first pension moment is gonna do that
process he's going to go through that
process first he picks on 26 kinds of
meditation that were popular in Tibet in
the 17th century and then he picks on
the Buddhist schools the lower Buddhist
schools okay after picking on the Hindu
schools so you pretty much get a review
of all the kinds of meditation that have
been done in the world except for Far
East likes China or Japan okay so if you
stick with this book which so far has
been seven years and we have I think
another seven years to go I don't know
I'm trying to finish by in five more
years and I have to choose me and
Veronica we have to choose a date in the
break maybe or something for the next
series for the next installment okay
which is comes out of her home time
which is why I'm embarrassing you in
front of everybody okay okay so here's a
breakdown of the conure okay and and
it's so you can appreciate Buddhism all
Buddhism in this world comes from the
Congo okay
all that's left in this world comes from
the Congo okay then
guess where I'm gonna go into the tenure
which is the explanations of the
Buddhist speech okay then where am I
gonna go
then I'm going to go into our
translation work to clarify the Tingler
okay which is where we're at upstairs
which is what we do upstairs
okay we try to cover all the schools of
Buddhism with about a team of about I
don't know a total team of about a
hundred translators okay ten primary
translators and about 90 secondary
translators in different languages we
have Mandarin French Arabic Spanish
Russian German basa
Indonesian and like that so there's a
huge team around the world working to
translate okay so here's the breakdown
at the conger okay
and Nick's in charge of that I think we
should give him a hand yeah and he's in
charge of other things too so the first
section in the conger is Val morality
it's seven titles and 13 volumes which
means certain titles are more than one
volume it's about twelve thousand pages
eight kinds of morality eight kinds of
moral codes taken by vow which is called
vinaya okay that's the first section of
the traditional thousand books okay yeah
and then the second section is called
shutter Sahasra Capretta bottom da which
means a perfection of wisdom in 100,000
lines this is one title in 12 volumes
over 11,000 pages it's a single book
about emptiness okay and it's the Buddha
teaching emptiness in a hundred thousand
lines okay of Sanskrit which in Tibetan
works out to about two hundred thousand
months okay the next section is called
Nietzsche in Tibetan which means twenty
thousand and if you're cool you know it
means 25 okay which is Vince Shetty a
punch of initiative which means 25
thousand lines so this is misspelled
and that's two volumes of 1900 pages and
these have all been completed me and
Jigme have finished this not translating
just naming okay the next one is the
eight thousand lines and this is
probably the most famous of all the
perfection of wisdom sutras okay it's
often printed as a separate book so so
in in most cases these books are rarely
printed separately from the conure they
are just part of the country if your
book made it into the conger it survived
for the last six hundred years if it
didn't make it into the country it died
and it disappeared in tibet you see
translations so this is the eight
thousand lines if it's amazing and you
know you when you study emptiness like
we are doing here it's dry and it's hard
it's gonna be drying hard tonight okay
and but in the old days it was science
fiction and it reads like a science
fiction book and it's really really cool
you know this basically a young man has
a has a voice in his head telling him to
walk east and he just takes off and
walks and he keeps having these what he
call like a flash back future flash back
he sees his teacher teaching a group of
disciples first like ten seconds and
then he's like who is that what are they
doing you know and the teachers teaching
emptiness to his disciples and he starts
having these visions of what's really
going on in this faraway city and he's
just drawn to the teacher like a magnet
and it's a it's a beautiful beautiful
story
his name is dr. move do you know
yeah nice I've got any penny money in
that um by the way Peter I have to give
the money from last night yeah his name
is soft flute or something
always weeping and the story is when he
reached the town where his teacher was
teaching his disciples he thought that
he couldn't go without an offering you
know he couldn't interrupt the class
unless he had an offering but by that
time he was broke because he had been
walking across the country of India and
then he he decided to sell his body to
sell pieces of his meat at the butcher
shop so he went to the butcher he said
can I sell the pieces of my arm my name
in the butcher said you know it's your
thing man and so he cut his flesh and he
was selling pounds of flesh and by the
way it's not a traditional practice
you're not supposed to do it no people
do stupid things anyway then the demons
blocked his sound of his voice so he
said and I was like what's that guy
trying to say nobody knows and out of
frustration he starts to weep and he's
weeping and then later he became known
as mr. cry-baby or something cuz he was
crying
do you know historians do you know what
happens to come on
so you're close can I get him yeah
there's a rich merchant who's had who's
beautiful daughter is out sunning
herself on the on the top of a building
around the square where the butcher shop
is and she she sees him and she's
attracted to him so she comes downstairs
and introduces herself and he says I
need money different offerings she says
I'm rich you know here unless and he
says you want to come with me and he
says yeah
and they both became disciples and they
lived happily ever after
okay that's the 8,000 percent but it's
it's amazing the book is amazing it it
reads like science fiction okay and the
next one is the perfection wisdom 18,000
lines I stood on her South Africa and
it's two thousand eight hundred fifty
pages we completed that section the next
one with the cat is the professionalism
in 10,000 lines so you have five
sections devoted to and thousands and
thousands of lines devoted just to
emptiness okay so you want to know what
the Buddha thought was important it was
emptiness okay and he just kept doing it
over again okay ten thousand nine
eighteen thousand months twenty five
thousand nine hundred thousand lines
okay and it's amazing and they're all
quite summer and they're often quoted
later okay next one this is called other
teachings on the perfection of wisdom
the Chitra protein a parameter and it's
31 books but this is where the Heart
Sutra is and this is where the diamond
cutter Sutra is these are their short
books on emptiness the short classics on
emptiness are here okay so I think
that's it's called searching not soak in
Tibetan this is the super sexy section
like short digestible presentations of
emptiness and amazing totally amazing
okay but there are sort of abbreviations
of those other books that might be
twelve volumes okay
I like this one it's called rotten
hakuta pile of jewels 49 books these are
short reference sutures that are often
used the meeting of the father and son
is there often times they are requested
by a bodhisattva sometimes they're
considered a single work with different
sections okay but 49 major sections okay
the meeting of the father and son where
Lord Buddha goes to teach his father
after his father died is there and it's
a Buddhist holiday the day he came back
which is called Sabah touching which
means the God fell down God felt God
dropped in again okay stop
God dropped down God returned okay next
one is called avatamsaka very famous
falchion in tibetan and it means
majority and tween we figured it out one
day we found the only reference in a
million pages that explains why it's
called the majority and then we lost it
and I can't tell you it's 52 books 5,000
pages the 10 Bodhisattva Davos focus
there the prayer of Samantha blood was
there these are very very important
later okay the next is section 10 is the
collection of sutras I was thinking to
force the translators to memorize all
these things but they kind of resist
stuff like that they just want to
translate and I can't blame them so
anyway it's 265 sutras out of a thousand
books right so this is 25 percent of the
country and this is where you find the
great sutras okay the great sutras of
all time and I just put the Lotus Sutra
there's a Sutra called odds on loom
which means the Sutra of the wise and
the foolish very cool often quoted in
the lamrim
journey to Lanka which is a very
important Sutra for emptiness and the
mind only school and gone but up so
which is what is that yeah
what I really meant son son Dean Sunday
near mochima
and this is where a body sufferer
confronts Lord Buddha and says why
you've been teaching different things
you know sometimes you say everything's
empty sometimes it's not
ACI course 15 okay some copper it's a
it's a reply to the question of when a
teacher teaches contradictory things is
it always that they're crazy or is there
some deeper reason okay and a buddy
Suffolk confronts Lord Buddha and since
explain yourself okay and we are working
on that in China I'll talk about it
later okay
section 11 is called a young day which
means a nirvana and these are teachings
that Lord Buddha gave in the last weeks
of his life and they're very bittersweet
they're very sweet and it's two great
sections here okay two great books
almost a thousand pages okay the last
one is called Vajrayana this is tantra
secret teachings and there are seven
hundred and thirty books okay
in the conure what percent of the Conger
is Tantra
come on out of a thousand bucks settle
her in 30 okay so almost 3/4 of the
conure it's a secret teachings and so
when people say the secret teachings are
not valid or or weird or something like
that you gotta understand the Buddha
taught over 700 of them directly okay so
and they're beautiful and they're
amazing and they're sweet and they're
pure okay and if you're lucky you get to
study them okay so that's there and
that's 20,000 pages of tundra so don't
tell me Tantra is weird or but it didn't
teach it okay it's it's 20,000 pages of
the country it's by far the largest
section in the country okay
all right then I was gonna show you a
breakdown of the tenure ten years
commentaries written on the Buddhist
teaching we had a blackout period 500 BC
to about 100 AD six or seven hundred
years there was a blackout period and
there wasn't much original work done
that's that's the abhidharma period in
Buddhism it's considered a dark a period
of darkness where people forgot when
emptiness men and they taught a much
lower version of emptiness for seven
hundred years and it's very dry I spent
12 years on it I memorized a lot of it
and it's very dry and a lot of it is is
the emptiness parts are incorrect but
the karma parts are famously correct and
all later presentations of karma come
from that so a lot of DCIM material
comes from those times okay so I thought
to give you a breakdown of the Tingler
just so you could appreciate the scope
of what me and jig may have to do in the
next 60 years if we're gonna finish okay
or we need help you know and again the
help just comes down to money okay
yeah we just you know people like Nick
they have this bad habit of eating every
single day and we tried for a long time
to do it with volunteers it doesn't work
it just doesn't work people need a
salary people need to have a place to
live they need to have a place to put
their puppies and stuff and that's the
reality of it and so we just a lot of my
life is fundraising nowadays a lot of my
time is spent fundraising and it's just
the reality we need to do it anyway if
you feel inspired by my talk you can
help us and it doesn't mean you have to
give money okay
helping to fundraise is a glorious
activity Christina and John just raised
a million dollars where is John yeah for
for cataloging without me I was I didn't
do one minute of work on it which was
the first time in my life that I haven't
had to do it and with a million dollars
and and because of that we are
cataloging three to five hundred
thousand books in Mongolia okay
and it's amazing it's totally amazing
and it's going and the government's
excited and everyone's excited about it
and it's amazing
Indiana Jones Brady okay so here's the
breakdown of the pinger okay and what I
did was I sprinkled in translations that
were working on to show you the strategy
we have of covering all the major
schools of ancient India so the
translations are spread out to all the
major schools of ancient India because
each major school has a different
vocabulary because they occupied
different centuries one not Aprilia with
a shorter sort of the drunked of march
half pairs at the bharata and bothered
every vein and swish local of which they
are to and gathered is the floor
Kathir okay but you have to teach people
this is you know you have to have a
Chaucer expert then you have to have a
Shakespeare expert then you have to have
I don't know summer sitting you got to
have different experts so we I want you
to see the structure of all Buddhism and
how we're covering it upstairs in the
translation room because it's a huge
strategy globally we have people working
in many many countries and it's
expensive and it's cool and it's working
and we're we're paying for it it's about
uh I know it's close to a million
dollars even look here we the first
section of tenure explanations how many
years of tenure are there start 100 AD
go up to around 850 yeah I call it 800
years of tenure ok 3,300 books something
like that 3000 some ok first it's called
stotra
which is songs of praise and this is
like usually it's the Lord Buddha and
you're so cool it's like Beatles songs
dedicated to the Buddha
okay and we're not translating those
because I don't know we don't have time
the next one is Vajrayana which is 2,600
books okay out of the out of the 3,000
six 700 books in the tenure two-thirds
are tundra ok so don't tell me Tantra is
not violent or something like that ok or
else two thirds of Buddhism is invalid
ok so anyway oops now I put Sadie's
photo there just because he's handsome
and now he's he was the last person to
join the translation team we didn't
intend to have him on the translation
team he begged to be on the translation
team we noticed he was really good with
languages
then I was in Vienna and two Austrians
approached me and said we want you to
your team to translate a book on karmic
correlations do this get this and I said
well there's two famous books one is by
the Buddha called which means all the
kinds of karma and Buddhist says in that
Sutra Buddha says you want to look nice
here's the Karma you want have money
here's the camera you want your wife to
wash the dishes here's the Karma okay
like it he breaks it down kind of my
Karma okay then a thousand no fifteen
hundred years later 15 centuries later a
dude named Elisha is headed for Tibet to
teach and his teacher Dharma rakshita
says you know I got some advice for you
because the two bands are bullheaded
people you know I got a book I wrote you
a book and he is when he's leaving for
Tibet his teacher hands him a book of
poetry
and says you're gonna need this if
you're gonna deal with those yak front
crazy young farmers who don't even have
an alphabet you know you're gonna need
this book of instructions and it's a
very beautiful book of commas it's a
book of Karma's and I used it from my
business book I stole everything from
there I think I even credited him but so
anyway say we decided that say gee he
would be the person to Austrians agreed
to fund him his salary and we started we
started on that second book and then we
mr. Wu took the first book and we went
we went on a on a two-volume karmic
correlations deal whopper and it's
amazing it's just amazing and we found a
commentary to our teachers teachers text
which is a public teaching which is a
public teaching by the by a lama
something that 300 years ago and then
the Lama got we didn't know it but the
Lama goes off on Tantra half the time
and so then you know in class everyone's
getting a big dose of secret teachings
upstairs and everyone's jealous of say
gee everyone says I want a damper anyway
so I put his book in secret section
because it's a tradition in Tibetan
Buddhism that if a book has a
significant amount of Tantra in it it
has to be counted catalogued in the
secret teachings okay it's a tradition
so your book is Tantra I'm sorry alright
but it's also a huge amount of low Jung
which is just how to be a good person
how to develop kind of basic kindness
compassion okay all right the second
section 3 is lower middle way which
contradictorily in the Congo and tenure
is called president parameter and see so
when you say Prajnaparamita in the
conure it means all teachings on
emptiness by the Buddha when you say
prayers no paramita in the tenure it
means only lower middle way okay only
the lower middle way okay so it's
confusing okay to represent that by the
way the main writer there is a Sangha
Arya Sangha who lived 17 centuries ago
okay and one of his most famous books is
I'll be somewhere Alan Carr I'm talking
on him in a jewel of realizations okay
and maybe the most famous line is denne
denne singing I'm getting insane on your
shoe Bay tangent dodging looted on luma
tomato purge a very famous it says what
do the lions dance meditation learn the
dying lion stands meditation and then
you will
look - looking dope yeah you'll know how
to how we get in trouble and you know
how to get out of trouble
good put the car in reverse okay so
we've been doing that at the Lamia
teachings for I don't know two years I
think we started in Mexico the lion
stance has five classical parts taught
by a Sangha - sorry
taught by my trailer - a Sangha in His
heaven and then he brought it back okay
and we've been going through it part by
part I think we're on the last part in
what we're gonna do it in July in Mexico
but it's a it's a preparation meditation
for emptiness it's very powerful
okay so there's a whole book about it
and so Gong she who's Chinese extraction
from Singapore and Indonesia he's
translating that book and he's a very
also a very talented linguist he said he
worked in Sony Corporation in Japan from
three years and or he touches somebody
like that and so his Japanese is very
good his Chinese is fluent and his
Indonesian is his mother tongue and
singlish Oh as English is quite good
he's a linguist so he's doing that book
higher middle way which is called
madhyamaka in the tenure okay
it's called maca okay although
technically sugan would be muddy muck
also okay but in the tenure it's not
laid out that way one hundred fifty
seven books seventeen volumes sixteen
thousand pages the first book I want to
talk about is next book 60 verses on
reasoning you want to describe it in two
sentences take lots of breath
it's one of the great books in the guard
unit which proves to the lower school I
described it this afternoon
okay first of the lower schools that
they already accept the higher schools
idea yeah and the person who wrote the
commentary is guilt of Jay some complex
disciple who when he met the greatest
master of Buddhism amber was already a
high master himself
specializing in logic so formal logical
syllogism study syllogism so he which is
how you see emptiness and it's extremely
difficult and we're having fun
frustrating ourselves with that book
next we have Ben Kramer he's doing a
book called Siddhanta in which we cover
all the schools of Buddhism it's a
survey of all the schools of thought
starting with the Hindu schools of
thought out of which Buddhism grew and
we're gonna be going through it tonight
and tomorrow in in this book called
angel and devil the angel debates the
devil okay I want to just point out the
completion dates here I mean say J 2023
sugeng 2022 Nick 2022 and we're putting
out a series of 108 books these will be
in this series you're welcome to be one
of the five people who buys one five
taels
I'll do four okay
and in bands it's 2021 he's pretty he's
up pretty soon
venerable Paulo is translating this is a
genre called Tati say Tati Tom means
view of emptiness team means specials
instructions and it's a whole book
dedicated to emptiness meditations and
we did some of it last night
and it's amazing it's extraordinary
so after sages class everybody says they
want sages book but then after it Paul
has a class everyone says they weren't
hurt but no one says that after Abbey
Dharma okay
section 5 karma commentaries on sutra ok
and this is not so this is where they
actually take a Sutra and they go
through it word by word ok in the tenure
and there's 38 titles there we're
working on two of them one is communist
commentary to the diamond cutter which
has never been taught that I'm aware of
and has never been translated a sense it
was first translated and it's the
longest commentary to the diamond cutter
it's 130 pages total and I taught it for
five years and I'm translating it for
another three four years okay and it'll
be done and it's an extraordinary
commentary it's extremely difficult
there are no commentaries on it and I
think some of it was translated from
Sanskrit by a guy who was drunk and I
mean it's really extremely difficult so
anyway when I was in college I had to do
report on Edgar Allan Poe who claimed
that he wrote most of his stuff drunk
and so I'd thought to write about that
okay
then we talked about the famous Sutra
called emotive cell which is where the
Buddhist says what I really meant you
can translate it the title as what I
really meant it's probably one of the
most important sutras of all time and
it's very interesting you see all the
tenure the 3500 books call it it's
written in Sanskrit right and translated
into Tibetan except for one book and
that's a commentary on what the Buddha
really meant written in Chinese okay and
the Tibetans considered it so important
that they translated it with the tenure
and this was written in the time of
chuan song which is around 700 AD 750 ad
okay
and it's 1,400 75 pages long it'll be
8,000 English pages okay and I'm planned
to finish it in 2034 so we're working on
it with a Chinese team some of the
Chinese still exists and some of it
doesn't
some cop I used it for his great work on
interpretation so it's true it's um
coming into the transmission so we're
doing the sutra within the chinese
commentary which would be eight seven
tonnes pages and then we're doing some
copper we're just throwing them all
together okay and we're making good
progress we're about a couple hundred
pages into it okay
that's the foundation of a program in
china called china's soft are we sold it
to the AI dee' the Asian infrastructure
investment bank which was funded by the
Chinese government for a hundred billion
dollars they took all their the US bonds
and put it into this Bank it's the third
World Bank in the world after the IMF
and the World Bank and they are building
infrastructure from Asia to Europe they
are building a new Silk Road and they're
spending a hundred billion dollars and
it's it's unbelievable basically Europe
and Asia will become one unit okay by
the time they're finished so we sold
them on the idea of training people
to use their ancient culture to be more
time gentle thoughtful do good karma
while you're out there taking over the
world okay alright so we're translating
that book as the foundation of that
program and all the people in the
program are in the translation class
also which is really cool and the
Chinese government is happy because
we're recovering a book that they lost
okay all right we don't say much that
you answer was from the author was born
in Korea he was Korean he wrote in
Chinese no he's a young man he came to
China and he never went back home but
his disciples started Buddhism in Korea
okay all right mind only school is the
most handsome translator there are 66
books there and word picked a book I
know he talked about it today I don't
have to say much about it it's quite
some copy it's called difficult points
in the mind only school we thought it
would be a nice survey of the mind only
school it turns out to be difficult
points into my noise we had a very rocky
start then we found a commentary to it a
more recent commentary in the last 3 400
years and it's great and we're working
through that and it's amazing it's a
totally amazing ok mine only school is
big in China because when Chinese
Buddhism went to China from India mind
only was the school of India so you know
the Chinese one point four billion
people really enjoy his work and they're
very appreciative of his work okay
section seven I'll be Dharma dry dry
seven hundred years of dryness and
Stanley Chan is working on that and it's
gonna finish in 2042
and we're on schedule okay and this is
what I'm trying to say this is the kind
of planning we have to do at this
institution we are working for
generations we are planning John's work
will be done in another 50 generations
okay
he's about 5% finished after 31 years
okay and the transaction will take about
30 generations okay and we are thinking
that we're here that's what we're that's
what we do here you know we we are
thinking on a very large scale of how to
protect this wisdom in this planet and
how to spread it in this planet in a
non-religious way in a way that everyone
can use we have last year I think 3,000
Muslims came to programs and Communist
Party members in China and we taught in
the Congress in Mexico to Catholics and
hardcore Catholics and and it's just
we're doing we're taking this wisdom and
exporting it to each country in a way
that they can enjoy and that they can
use for them so okay without having to
sign up for Buddhism okay so that's
damaging we picked the youngest
translator to do thousand 40 he will be
[Music]
50-something he'll be 57 when he
finishes and he's into it he's really
getting into it he's found the Chinese
commentaries and he's really into it now
it was a little bit of a rocky start he
really didn't want to do it his partner
Allison joel is working on vinaya and we
are working through the fall nuns vows
which have been lost in Tibet for a
thousand years and it's amazing and the
work is extraordinary the work is like
going to another planet because no one
has worked on this for a thousand years
and the vows are amazing and we're
recovering them we we have I don't know
100 commentaries in John Brady's
database from two and a half thousand
years ago so we are putting it back
together and nuns will be able to keep
all the many more vows no okay
the next section I'm going to The Ting
you're okay
it's called Jessica which is stories of
the birth of the but why are we doing
this tonight somebody remind me because
the author is gonna do it he's gonna go
through each of these schools and I want
you to know I want to say but this is
Stanley's this part Stanley this part
Allison I want you to say oh yeah you
told us about that right you're not
gonna forget it before tomorrow okay the
day after it's okay so this is where the
Buddha explains karma and dr. Wu is
working on which is very very cool
because the Chinese still exists so
we're able to cross-reference the
Chinese the Sanskrit still exists and
the Tibetan still exists so and Ayesha
found the Sanskrit and we should give
her a hand
[Applause]
Nabby
lovey anyway it's amazing and so we're
able to use all three languages and we
have experts in all three languages and
young tongue which his assistant is
working on it with him okay and they're
doing a nice job the story of the boy
who gets shipwrecked and goes - you know
who kicked his mother by accident that
comes from there which is the basis of
Sage's book which so they're starting to
be this what do you call it
incest wholly incest all these great
books are starting to overlap
you know like vinaya emptiness comes up
in vinaya and and then you know
abhidharma is treating karma and karma
being taught downstairs here on the same
day and the DCI teacher training and
there's amazing stuff going on okay
we're using all of it and and what's
going on at this school is is going at a
thousand miles an hour you know people
who haven't been here for a year coming
they say uh what's going on you know
we're like yeah we found some more stuff
upstairs you know and we use it
immediately in DCI programs like we just
got back from Vienna and Japan and we
used we use the new text we use the
different we used to gangs' text in
Japan and China and Vienna and we just
through a whole new thing and it's
really cool
so it's like a moving target okay and I
I meet friends who came to my classes in
80's and 90's and and they're like okay
section ten epistles that car and these
are letters written by saints - mostly
kings and that we just closed the deal
with the Japanese publisher to translate
three of them which are two Greek and
Indian Kings to binder Gardiner and one
by Naga Sina and they are amazing and
they're amazing for their effect on
Greek culture
taught to breakings in India by Buddhist
monks and the story of emptiness of the
the cart comes from there and things
like that amazing things that we use
every day and DCI okay and we'll be
working on those god bless section 11 is
school number two which is what style
treinta which is it's called logic but I
hit the card back because people fall
asleep I just say the word logic and
they fall asleep but it's clear thinking
nowadays I like to call it clear
thinking how to think clearly and Adam
Adams
working on that book he'll be done in
2032 okay and it is the greatest book on
Dhamma kitty okay he's translating the
greatest commentary on this subject and
which is called the key to emptiness it
is said in Buddhist circles that if you
don't understand how to think clearly
you cannot see emptiness you have to
study this topic to see emptiness
directly okay and we teach that in this
year number seven we use it extensively
we use that commentary extensively okay
okay now then there's a couple sections
that are not we don't we're not
translating Sanskrit language studies
which are really obscure and you're
better off studying a grammar by one of
the modern comedians Dwight Whitney from
Yale who was my teachers teachers
teacher in the 1800s he wrote the best
but you don't need this book to it's a
better presentation sentence within here
okay medicine tickets a Vidya it's
interesting because Tibet is halfway
between China and as far as medicinal
theory classical Chinese medicine and
Ayurveda Tibet is a mixture and it's
quite it's quite interesting and there
are great commentaries I studied and I
translated for the dynamics doctor for a
couple of years and
they're amazing they're very very
beautiful we don't have time to work on
it we have fine arts painting sculpture
architecture okay some great classics
there and then Nettie Shastra which
means worldly topics my favorite book
there is a book on what do you call it
not kama Sutra there's a book on how to
evaluate gemstones and that I really
enjoy but generally they're not they're
not like books that we want to spend
most of our life on and then there's a
book there's a whole section of 118
books called stuff we didn't know where
to put it and it's really cute and it's
all kinds of weird stuff in there okay
so that's to show you how the schools
that you're gonna go through in this
text are being covered in this
institution by this College and the
players go up to about 2,000 42 and
we're working we're working through it
so I thought you would maybe you'd like
to get involved on some level you know
anyone in this room can get involved
talk to Nick if you'd like to you don't
have to be a Sanskrit translator you can
help there's there's tons of stuff to do
there's a whole lifetime of stuff to do
and we don't leave it on the library
shelves we interpret it for the modern
world and we bring it down here and we
teach it to 30,000 people every year and
the Mexican team who's can't hit welcome
we should give them a hand
they've been working with a crew of
people guardians under people who have
gotten Congress of Mexico to pass a law
that good a good eating good stretching
and see thinking from this you know must
be taught in hundred thirty thousand
Mexican schools to twenty three million
children okay so Kearney is in charge in
our planning and if you guys do a good
job
you could affect more people than I have
in my whole life
you see if you guys just do a good job
we're gonna have a big meeting tomorrow
you would affect more people than we've
ever been able to touch you see and and
we're working on obesity and bullying
and self-esteem and but have a good
eating and and treating people according
to the golden rule so I think it's gonna
be you basically have a chance to remake
a country if you work hard so that's
kind of cool
okay alright let's go back to the text
I'll do 15 minutes of text we'll take a
break okay and I'm gonna have a meeting
upstairs during the break with some of
you and I'll let you know who okay okay
so here we go to the text which you can
take me off the screen Peter I don't
know if that's you guys can do that I
prefer that you hear the text verbally
which is the ancient tradition and then
I've translated the text for you and you
have done and then I've also written a
flowchart out the ideas because unless
you're very familiar with all the
subjects we just talked about you can't
see any flow to this book and there is
no commentary okay so here we go
alright last night we were studying a
famous proof of emptiness called neither
one nor many okay things are neither one
nor men
and the way they get and and let me
clarify okay don't get don't get lost
okay the gardener
after 700 dark years and Bobby Dharma
280 he shows up and nicks book and his
system is cool his whole life okay first
of all he's called the iron
his nickname is Harper which is just the
dude who saw emptyness directly
that's his unofficial name what's his
other unofficial name the second Buddha
to walk this earth so he was amazing and
he he's famous for having seen emptiness
directly and his main thrust of his
teaching was to say there's something
screwy going on didn't you notice you
see okay
and when you really study in the garden
and you spend years on the garden
frustrated earth trying to break through
in the garden then you realize his big
stick is didn't you notice there's
something weird going on you know like
the way we think about stuff it doesn't
work exactly right you see and his first
thing is to attack the idea of one thing
okay he says there's something weird
about one thing you know there's
something weird going on you know what
you know so it's called the argument of
things are not one okay and things are
not more than one you can say one in
many but I think a better translation is
things are not one no thing in the
universe is a single thing nor is it
more okay and and then you're like come
on
my stomach's a thing fill it up every
day you know doughnuts art thing pizzas
are you know all the important stuff is
there one thing you know you haven't
been looking closely some nudes going on
you know so he devoted his life to
trying to shake up people say look it
ain't the way it looks you know it's not
what you think
you know
there's signs of problems and one of
them is is that nothing to what things
and then you're like come on what are
you talking about okay so we did it last
night
okay and we didn't finish we covered all
the major categories of existence we
covered changing things and I'm changing
things inside of changing things we
covered physical things mental things
and changing things starting at mental
physical then we went to on changing
things and went deep because we covered
three different kinds empty space which
never changes
yes cessation is permanent endings of
negativities the end of anger in a human
soul okay
like never changes okay and is it one
thing you see and and it's empty space
one thing what was the third example
emptiness itself
okay so he covers every major category
of existence and he examines them to see
if things are one thing okay and he says
no and we you know we went in depth in
the atom thing but you could you could
do the mind flow thing you could do the
emptiness of different objects in this
room what's the border between the
Antonis of Bonnie and the emptiness of
ring where is the border you can't find
it okay and you live with that like you
don't get upset
you don't like they come in Ric and
Bonnie and you're like guy Rick your
buddy I can't see this border between
your emptinesses you know like no one
freaked out when they came you know I
can't see the border between your
antennas because we got used to it you
see we got we got used to just fuzzy
it's I can't see the back of Rick right
now for all I know he's a robot and
there's a big key in the back and she
turns it every morning and you know no I
mean but my mind feels in my mind fills
in the rest of Rick you see and and then
I take that as Rick
okay but based on the parts I only can
see a few parts now okay by the way if
you see his right arm you can't see his
left arm at the same time okay you can
on you ready and you cannot see his
right arm unless you see his fingers
okay right I mean just be a kind of a
stick right and you can't these fingers
unless you see the five fingers or for
whatever he's gone certified let's get
five but you can't see the thumb unless
you see the little finger you see you
can't certify five unless you see them
one by one you cannot and the human eye
cannot see all five at once cannot or it
would look like a glove or something
when you call a mitten it would look
like a mitten so and I know it sounds
stupid or unnecessary or just philosophy
but what's the punchline it's not a bit
it's not coming at me okay how do I see
Rick's right arm
it comes from my seats in my own mind
you see I'm creating his right arm okay
get on so that's almost as uselessness
as you know arguing about how many
finger you said I mean yeah but the
guardian says look something else is
coming weird you know just flipping the
switch turn the light on in the room huh
when you want the light on what do you
go do you gone flips you say I can't
find the switch it's dark in here I
can't find the switch okay right and
whenever you flip the switch to like
this on right this is something
developed in DC I it's really cool
DCI moves really fast
why am i doing that I did this the first
time in Earp and outside of Kiev
the audience was half Russian half
Ukrainian which itself was an
achievement why doing that and I said I
have to do this and they're like I gotta
make the Sun come up tomorrow I gotta do
this before it gets too late I'm making
the Sun come up tomorrow
nothing no listen every time I bring in
the mic the Sun comes out the next day
and every time I flip the switch the
lights keep flipping switches keep
working for those money okay keep
looking online for a nice boy or girl
got it
everything you do is mistaken everything
every single thing you ever do to get
anything is mistake the Guardians like
wake up you know sometimes you turn this
light switch in the light doesn't go on
yeah but that's cuz the light burned
down yeah but if the switch made the
light go on they would go on anyway look
but it only makes it go on sometimes
she's like are you crazy you just told
me the truth okay you're right nothing's
working the way you thought it was
nothing okay and every time you flip a
light switch what do we say last time
last night
every time you flip a light switch to
turn a light on you
you you you reinforce the
misunderstanding of your world and it
will get you deeper and deeper into
misery and things won't work you know
and you will die and your body will wear
out and you'll just be one of those
people who died I get emails you
wouldn't believe it it's super
depressing I don't see people for five
years 10 years 20 years I always get the
death email
I always but now I have a failed disease
get to live teach me Buddhism email you
know like 10 years later all right
everybody every single person I get that
it's frustrating you know should have
come to me ten years ago you know I
can't help you no I can't teach you
everything in three days or three weeks
you see I mean then people send me Oh
things didn't work out all right
understand so what the Guardian is
saying and what the pension mama sing is
that the emptiness of one in many boils
down to the emptiness of one thing and I
cannot be seeing Rick the way I think
I'm seeing because it's not possible I
can't look at your left arm and see your
right arm but if I don't see your left
arm and your right arm I can't see you
okay so something else is going on your
eye is not jumping around and getting
indicator and then synthesizing Rick
it's now it's happening it's come from
you okay
that's one ring okay that's why there's
no - Rick's that's Barney he's unique
right so anyway now now that we've
studied what it means to not be one or
many which really just means not to be
one because if it's not one yeah if you
don't have one output you can drop off
so we don't have to talk about more than
what he proved one ring
he can't be if he has parts which we
established for every category of
existing thing last night if he has part
I cannot see the whole it's not possible
what's going on is
is something weird something weirds
going on and the gardener says because
it's coming from you how you see
indicators you see skin colors brown
spots long spots and then a seat opens
in your mind and a picture comes out
called Rick and you and synthesizes Rick
into ring okay so Rick's coming from me
not from me okay
so try to find one Rick who's coming
from Rick Stein you ain't gonna find Amy
okay if so is it true that there's no
one ring true or false
yeah you gotta say that Rick who comes
from me that okay okay maybe so when the
gardener comes and says it's the Antle
is it possible when things are one or
more than one you say yeah and said why
is it cuz coming from me but if you said
not coming from me then it's impossible
okay got it
something screwy's going on get this
feeling okay now let's go to the text
okay how do you use it in your real life
okay
that's the pension laws favorite subject
okay so I'm
[Music]
yeah we finished we took along here we
finished on that I'm on 120 okay I'm on
verse 120 you don't have to look at the
text just listen tonight when you're
overwhelmed it's more curiosity to go
deeper you can look at the text okay
verse 120 is another ineffective
meditation politely out of wanting to be
polite
I call it ineffective meditation so you
could call it stupid meditations but
it's not nice to say those things okay
so ineffective meditation number 13
decide that things are neither one nor
many but don't use it okay so now we got
sophisticated we got someone who sat in
the room on Saturday 9:00 and heard the
one or many argument about rig okay and
they went home and they never used it
okay so that's that's called useless
meditation okay oh look
Rex neither one nor many okay and then
you just go on with your life so how are
you gonna use it for example how's
Bonnie gonna use Ric's emptiness to have
a even sweeter marriage next year huh if
he's not one of many it means he's
coming from me
he's coming from you right so the next
time he does something stupid who are
you gonna yell at
No then you have to pat yourself on the
back
don't tell him he's good no I'm just
saying use it use it okay oh you have
everyone has problems with their
partners come on let's be honest you
know you know don't get upset don't get
angry don't do things that don't work
okay
change your seats
okay change your seats and then the
person will change okay the person will
change
Oh my partner's addicted to so-and-so
okay so you stopped your addictions you
deal with one of your addictions and
then suddenly your partner doesn't have
this addiction anymore okay got it
I understand so the Buddhist method of
dealing with a marriage a partner is to
fix it here okay got it
that's why we study one and many and and
if you study one in many and you don't
try to fix your partner you didn't get
it okay got it that's where he is that's
verse 120 okay yes thanks knit Rick is
neither one or many okay see ya see you
next time okay
no use it make him wash the dishes come
on there's a famous story in DC I wear
this lady in Asia who I won't even name
the country because your guests said
that heard goal in her relationship was
that her husband should wash the dishes
all the time and I taught her the four
steps she invited me to her house the
next year and we sat down for dinner and
there was a bell on the table and she
she sat down and she rang the bell and
the kitchen door open and her husband
came out with an apron on many an Asian
never cooked okay
never ever and he's like yes dear and
she's like he's dinner and he and she's
like he's like oh no I'm so sorry I'm
almost done you know he went back in the
kitchen she said
five we were like you know it's a damn
your goal was to make it much the dishes
she said yeah but why stop there
you know the verse number hundred and
twenty is the person who studied one and
many who didn't use it to make their
husband washing dishes okay got it okay
they understood the concept they
understood the seed concept but they
didn't use it okay got it all right I'm
gonna give me five more minutes I'll
give you a break okay by the way there's
a large group of people here I don't
want you to come upstairs with me so I
can rant at you about something okay
in the break okay it's too many people
here yeah okay if you've been involved
for a couple years come upstairs at the
break okay I have a I have a lecture a
mini lecture okay all right cool
especially teachers okay all right any
effective meditation number fourteen
verse number hundred twenty one my
husband comes from my mental seeds the
Karma opens and a mental image comes out
and it coats him and and the parts are
unified into Rick who doesn't wash the
dishes okay got it and that's exactly
how it happens when do you what's the
Buddhist name for that process dependent
origination okay when do you see it
directly for the first time
yeah in the hours before you see
emptiness directly you see a karmic seed
opening your mind and you see it create
something in front of you okay and then
there's no more philosophy it's just
like you saw it okay
is that emptiness yeah and that's
ineffective number fourteen okay
oh let me meditate on the seed opening
in my mind that creates my rig okay and
and if you stop there and you don't go
further you have failed in Mahamudra
meditation okay got it is it useful
extremely I mean dishes is dishes okay
it's extremely useful but it's not the
ultimate goal all right by the way he's
and Nick's gonna explain it okay barring
which human computer is going to explain
it he says the problem in number 121 is
that you are focusing on a Mayan GOG am
i in and not a memo yeah say it again
you're talking about the problem is that
you're focusing on something not being
something else implying that it could be
there as opposed to something that's
just not there altogether yeah and and I
want to repeat the example from last
night it's a little weird but I think
everyone can relate to it okay so you
come home your husband is like this and
he's like giggling turn side and then
the minute you walk in the door he's
like you know and you're like who was
done and he's like what and like you
know who are you texting you know and
she's like hey nobody you know and and
then immediately the the man gets this
image in his mind of another man you see
and it the whole thing is very elaborate
you know like in the next few hours
every man knows this feeling I think in
the next few hours you're going to
create a very clear picture of
recipient of the email you know there's
gonna be and he's chasing your wife
around and that's where she was last
week when she said you know and you got
all this story of a guy in your mind
right very very strong picture in your
mind okay then we gave the example that
you guys go to bed and you wait til your
wife's asleep and then you sneak around
to her side of the bed and you duck down
because it makes a light that wakes up
people and you like hold it this way and
you check her the record of her texts
and she was texting Amazon to buy your
birthday present and that's why she was
excited okay why did we bring that up
poof lots of proof yeah the guy yeah
that's the point here okay that's the
point here your perception in your mind
your painting of this guy goes oh okay
it doesn't go
it just goes okay in one second it goes
and and that's emptiness okay emptiness
is not oh it's the other guy it's not
the guy thought it was okay it's not
thinking emptiness is not thinking oh it
wasn't what I thought it was it was this
okay got it
that's not emptiness that's what he's
trying to say it's not misidentification
of the object of the you're not thinking
oh it was Amazon instead of Joe okay
you're not thinking that what happens
okay that's emptiness okay something
that never existed
disappears okay and then suddenly you're
happy got in okay so in this now he's
going deeper and deeper into Buddhist
schools who misidentified emptiness
what's the point
what's the point yeah but what's the
point of that what's what's the point of
trying to go to poof when you could go
to my husband wash the dishes if I
handle the seed cards correctly yeah the
second one solves all your problems and
nothing else does okay I'll tell you can
boost things that you don't like you are
just improving the crap in your life
you're upgrading correct Peter they want
to bring okay go ahead it better be good
this seems this seems to imply that it
is possible to see dependent origination
and then not emptiness directly correct
that's the last stage of the second path
is to see the dependent origination
directly and then the next hour so you
see emptiness directly it's it is it is
always the case that you don't see
emptiness directly at the same time no
you don't it's impossible to have that
karma
take it then that meditation
oh no no yeah well it wasn't perfect
anyway okay yeah I understand it wasn't
your lunch a job but it was getting
there which brings up a nice subject
then what really stop okay
if you understand these faulty
meditations it's very useful each one of
them is very useful the lower schools
are useful okay if you really want to
understand emptiness then master these
26 wrong meditations and use them and
try them because it will take you higher
okay he's not picking stupid meditations
he's picking sophisticated meditations
that could take you higher okay got it
just like that tenure okay
90% of tenure is wrong well not if you
count enter but okay okay do you ready
here we go again
[Music]
Nik
the devil says if you identified that
Rick is coming from a seat in your mind
okay it doesn't hurt me directly why
what do you think
yeah it's not poof it's not a proof
experience okay that's the next verse in
the text okay it it doesn't hurt the
misunderstanding in your mind - it
doesn't really how do you say there's a
cowboy movie in the United States called
they say this town ain't big enough for
both of us
this is very common in the u.s. English
they say this town isn't the bad guy and
the good guy have guns and they said one
of us has to leave this town so it's
like that okay in your mind either you
are remembering that this person is
coming from you or you're not and if
you're not then the devil can stay okay
if you're not actively thinking so this
goes back to two states of mind that we
use in meditation called shaking and
timber somebody explain the difference
in this case Rick's wife is mad at him
for some irritating thing he did then
she gets shaken and you start getting
upset okay and then shaken in medic okay
wait describe Shane in meditation it
detects your texting okay and now
agitation mean in normal life when
Bonnie gets irritated at the records
never happens but just talk potassium
via Ripa for no dollars
in the highly hypothetical case I'm
trying to teach him this logic word and
it's been a struggle in the highly
theoretical case that Bonnie got he
rotated and her husband where's the demo
in meditation yeah so jumba means it's
mistranslated as a recollection it
doesn't mean recognize it means gamba
means to Paul so I means Paul the mind
back to the object you know bring them
right back okay they'll arm goes off and
then you bring the mind back so what's
the chamber in this case with Bonnie and
ring yeah you remember he's coming from
me the old one goes poof the one who's
not coming from you goes poof that's the
Peter and Maria do it last night right
and then then all it's good because then
you realize that you can change him and
you can change him again not by hurting
him or not by saying hard things to him
or you know not by being angry at him
but by changing him here okay all right
but until there's some Nina nice
discrepancy between what
yeah what's really there and what you
think you see so this is a big subject
in in Buddhism what's the Sanskrit Maya
illusion
okay so illusion in Buddhism just means
what you think you see and what's really
there they don't match they don't match
and that's the definition of illusion in
Buddhism okay so until there's a
discrepancy between the devil and angel
the devil will stay okay until there's
an active understand and tell there's an
active poof in body's mind she will
continue to be upset at Rick and there's
no other way according to Buddhism you
will never be totally patient with Rick
unless you can prove him okay not
possible okay all right now verse 123
okay
in effective meditation number 15 using
one and many to come to a lack of me but
why still holding in the in the octave
holding me what's a common example of
this problem in DCI I'll say it again
four does you've been doing construction
all day you gotta lay off like take
sunday off using the idea of one in many
there's no one and there's no many to
come to a lack of me but you are still
holding to me while you're doing that
what's a common DCI example while I'm
explaining to you why the pen comes from
you in that moment you are feeling that
it comes from answer okay and this is
just about anyone who's not an are you
in the direct perception okay even and
are you out of the direct mister did you
do the magic show today yeah if you came
to her magic show did you get through
the whole thing Wow
eight minutes
oh my god cool nice time okay so he's
talking about your you're thinking about
Oh Nick Ric's coming from me but but
while you're looking at him you still
feel like he's coming from him okay like
it's a it's a inability to implement it
completely in the moment
okay that's ineffective meditation
number 15 so you're getting
sophisticated you're understanding that
things are coming from you and you're
looking at him with irritation saying
he's coming from me which means you
think he's coming from him deep down got
it
so discrepancy between your feelings and
your and your understanding they don't
match yet I can't got it that's a deeper
kind of bad man attention it's okay if I
go like 10 minutes over because I
cheated you out of ten minutes it's from
15 it's okay if you have to go go if you
have to cut your subway or something
there's one across the street
[Music]
yeah and then the next verse is just a
very funny statement from ignorance who
says you know look man I'd love to leave
your mind but as long as you keep doing
this stuff I gotta stay here I'm sorry I
would like to leave I'm up for it I'm
willing to leave but as long as you're
thinking about the pan coming from its
own side while I'm explaining the pan
dear what's the man gonna do he got a
stink okay got it
it's kind of funny all right 125 versus
125 and this is a famous a quotation
from the three principal paths how do
you spell that principal
yeah I will personally decapitate any
person who puts ple which is not an
adjective it's only been 40 years anyway
okay
Macbeth Tessa kyon-kun Cigna last last
verse or next last verse my potential
client come Cigna means if your opinion
deserves of what is real if your opinion
of what is real dissolves and Macbeth
tests on me sir
if the way in which you view the object
which is like symptom you know taste so
as much ancient more ancient symptom is
how do you hold the thing so make the
texture kyon-kun cheaper means if it
dissolves
they'd say who made our top a lot then
you understand middle way okay that's
some copper so based on those on that
poetry
there was a school that came up in Tibet
where they said we are beyond all
positions we hold no positions we are
beyond philosophy we we exist in the
void you see and they really took it
seriously you know they said don't say
it's there and don't say it's not there
don't say Rick is there and don't say
Rick is not there just stay in
suspension it's all like the suspension
school and you know you kind of laugh or
something but if you were there in those
days you would have been a suspension
trust me that's the spender
okay often think that if I was in
Germany and thinking what 39 I I
probably would not have been brave
enough to not do what everyone else was
doing
you see I mean we we tend to do what
people around us do you see no matter
you know your opinion of yourself it's
probably exaggerated okay
so verse 125 is don't get fooled into
this school of thought that says it's
it's not meaningful to discuss
philosophy it's a waste of time it's
splitting hairs okay let's just leave it
be in your natural state because the
natural state of the mind is to suffer
okay is to misunderstand reality which
causes your suffering so you must repent
Ayyappa for $50 infinite okay it's a
very common expression in my jamika okay
50 bucks Peter to the construction guy
[Music]
you know people who say that look this
is all just I had a guy tell me that
someone left the door they said gets
lost too much you explain too much just
let it you know give us a couple of
months with no teaching you know and I'm
like don't tell you about this is the
position of the guys you know you know
you have to hear a thousand different
presentations and then it will sink into
the wood okay
and then the devil says an interesting
thing he says can I ask you a question
you know I'm the guy fine yeah okay and
he says like you're trying to hurt me
right that the word in Tibetan is no
yeah you're trying to damage me you are
trying to inflict damage on me
I'm the one who's in your mind telling
you to yell at your husband because he
decided to yell at you okay and the
angel is one the party of mine which
understands that you created your
husband and if you don't like it be
nicer to other people okay that's okay
so misunderstanding comes out to the
gynesis so I and the conversation is
really hilarious in Tibetan and I'm
sorry I can't do it very well
look what you try to do to me again and
the angel says we are trusting you out
of this mind you will be homeless you
know we are thrusting the wrong way of
looking at your husband
out of your mind forever you know he
says oh really he keeps doing that he's
like oh really
and you're gonna do that by taking no
positions at all right okay get it it's
a joke
okay you're gonna trust these wrong
ideas out of your mind by actively
taking no positions he says I like him I
go for that I bought for that okay okay
[Music]
now more deep okay
the devil says I have a new meditation
for you and the Angels like what and he
says how did you figure out that Rick
wasn't there okay the Peter and Maria's
demonstration which you guys got to work
on by the way and there's better ways
you know maybe if you had more fights
anyway so he says the devil says so
let's just
I thought we thought Robert De Niro
movie wasn't a silver lining or
something like that
it I feel like it's Robert De Niro
talking like the devil right he's like
he's like so you know like you you let
me get the strength you you figured out
that Rick wasn't real right and then
Bonnie says right and you know like you
figured out that the Rick you thought
was coming from Rick and Rick was being
mean because Rick wanted to be mean okay
which doesn't exist poof rent Rick's
mean because you were mean to somebody
else right makes not mean because Rick
decided to be mean the record decided me
mean doesn't exist okay
poof right so then the devil says so you
got it right you figured it out right
and we say yeah I figured it out what
what happened exactly how did you figure
it out and I said yeah you know you know
I wasn't doing anything on Saturday so I
decided to go to give him his class and
and Peter Maria did this nice
demonstration and you know I heard about
the ancient devil talk and
you know I studied in and I went home
and I didn't just put it on the shelf to
collect dust I actually read it the next
day a couple times I tried to figure out
how the outline matched the verses you
know and then I understood that Rick
wasn't coming from Rick and the devil
says well tell me more tell me more you
know like how did it feel and you know
what kind of things thoughts that you
have and then he the point is the next
kind of meditation is an over interest
in the proximate causes of seeing
emptiness directly in this day I level
seven we discussed the ultimate causes
and then we discussed the apparent
causes right so the apparent causes of
her figuring out that Rick is not coming
from himself was gesh last class the
poetry by the pension Lama
you know discussion with friends events
of the afternoon hearing these great
translators by the way these are last
year's production of the translators and
you should look at it I mean you should
look it's amazing it's amazing anyway so
what's the real cause of understanding
that your husband comes from you and not
from himself what's the what's the
deeper cause and what's the apparent
causes yeah sharing but what's the text
always say sharing
good yeah that the Tibetan is always the
same logician Djemba Djemba teach as
much as you understand the implication
is do you notice them much but share as
much as you can okay
like every chance you get that doesn't
bother other people okay which is not
allowed in Buddhism you cannot bang on
people's doors and ask her if they heard
about the pen I often do it on planes
though you know people say what do you
do for a living I pull out the pen
because you asked me okay and sorry but
to share with others as much as you
understand is the real cost of
understanding that your husband is
coming from you okay got it
it's not even going to class why hundred
dollar question it's not bad she said
it's like securing license Peter wait
Peter had he actually raised him but
he's Austrian okay got it
who wrote the diamond cutter Sutra like
okay when you go to see a movie I always
laugh at people who say you know I went
to see this movie about hate the ending
I'm like
who maybe I mean according to this
belief you made the ending okay and if
you come to this class and you have a
breakthrough and you suddenly understand
that Rick comes from you whenever is
irritating
and you're just striving your life not
to be here attending to other people if
you get the teaching it's only because
you shared what as much as you
understood with other people in your
life okay cool and that's now that
becomes more subtle okay
the devil says oh tell me again the
mighty deeds you did to understand Rick
you know and he wants you going off on
all the classes you in turn all the
books you Chancellor he wants you
distracted with all the stuff you did
rather than understanding that your
understanding comes from sharing
understanding okay cool and upstairs I
was mean to everybody and I wasn't
yelling at people for teaching I don't
mean to I exist to see your teach the
reason I'm doing what I do is I want to
see you teach but teach teach teach
wisely okay all right all right here we
go but don't not teach that would be a
big mistake all right
okay now so did I lose 100 who wasn't
are you paying sir
this is a perception okay
[Music]
hundred dollars okay it's not that I
have a lot of money I just want you to
listen hundred dollar question there's
been a theme throughout this poem about
a weakness of getting too interested in
the mental process who can tell me why
there's a been a theme that I've
mentioned a few times in this column of
a weakness of getting too interested in
the mental process that you use to get
to emptiness
tim has opinion
close but no cigar and I thought he
missed the human computer giving us
something else a brick you got rich off
me you're getting kind of close but not
really
okay Chen's on give me a shot okay Peter
it's more simple than that add too much
detail
okay I saved 100 bucks I mean I only go
so far you know if people gets fishing
around
sometimes I go ninety-eight didn't you
owe me okay
the human mind is defective okay
anytime you watch the human mind you are
worsening the infection okay
anytime you watch the human mind which
is defective because it thinks the pain
comes from itself any time you focus
just on the mind like watching mind just
itself the impure mind you become more
impure
okay if there's no active attempt to see
why it's coming from you okay okay this
is a theme throughout this book okay
until you are doing something which is
incompatible with misunderstanding you
are supporting misunderstanding
okay got it until you do something to
actively push it out you are supporting
it you're reinforcing it okay got it
it's weird which is to say if you ever
get upset at another person ever you are
reinforcing ignorance in your own mind
by the act of being irritated
so it's almost hopeless okay hearing
okay I'm gonna go to 9:30 so okay you
guys don't care that if you gotta leave
leave okay
we will next week we got some in the
fridge just heat it up don't don't tell
the dog all right yeah again ineffective
medication 18 verse number 129 is and I
could go off on it I could read you the
verse but the basic thing is study
without application okay and I think you
know having gone through the getchu
course 25 years in the monastery there
are times in the monastery when you get
really frustrated with people and you're
like you know there's a lot of politics
in a Buddhist monastery a those
institutions are the most important
institutions on this planet they're the
most precious institutions on this
planet B there's a lot of and a lot of
hard stuff goes down and sometimes
you're just stunned you know like I
heard you given our defense of this idea
about irritation and now you're so angry
at this other monk you know what's
what's going on okay so the devil here
says I like this kind of stuff I'm
especially enamored of people who study
study study and are still getting
irritated you know that somehow they can
get you Michael talk about irritation
for days and then go home and get
irritated within 15 minutes okay I'm
especially you're especially dear to my
heart
okay that's verse 129
okay verse 1 30 he repeats that
reviewing the thought flow that got you
to see that Rick was not coming from his
own sign it's not itself the perception
of emptiness okay and and this I love a
sermon we spend a lot of time on the
proximate causes the approximate cause
itself seeing emptiness directly I think
they say a lot of sermon is exciting
it's the only piece of literature I've
ever seen which is a guidebook to see
emptiness directly and it's I don't know
it's 200 300 pages long I think it's a
good piece of work but a lot of it is
tracing the thought process and the
devil here would say I hope you get
stuck on that okay I like it I hope you
never get to the end of the manual I
hope you keep thinking about how to get
the thought process going and you get
focused on the thought process and then
when you get home from DC at level seven
you yell at your husband then your
perfect okay
got it CS Lewis wrote a book I like to
talk about it what's it called
there's good tape letters and if you
haven't read it you should read it read
it it's it's about a young man in the
world war two and the devil assigns his
nephew to corrupt the young man and make
sure he doesn't go to heaven and and
it's a series of correspondences between
the uncle and his nephew
so the nephew is a junior devil and the
uncle is like the senior devil and he's
sending advice to his nephew about how
to corrupt this guy and keep him out of
heaven and it's and CS Lewis wrote it
who wrote the Narnia tales and the witch
in the Wardrobe
the land so he's a wonderful writer and
amazing thinker and so he says he said
it was the hardest thing he ever did in
his life to write the book because he
had to put his mind in the devil's of
mine and he said it was extremely
uncomfortable and it was like disgusting
like he felt revolted as he was writing
the book to put his mind in the devil's
mind so I think you could go to a dark
place following if you really understood
the ideas of this text which are very
sophisticated I think it would be a very
dark place to go I think it would take a
lot of strength to really put your mind
in the devil's mind and and try to make
sure people slightly missed the mark and
end up fighting with their wife when
they get home after the lecture all
right okay so and 131 and we have five
more minutes okay focusing on no
self-nature
but still not applying it to your life
and your challenges okay so I think a
special application of angel devil
thinking is with personal problems like
for me it was dealing with security bros
this week I I was contacted twice this
week and it was frightening and it's
difficult and and and I want to get
upset at somebody and then I'm the
devil's like calm down
you know to use it for challenges in
your life okay so don't we started with
irritating husbands and Rick as a topic
assembly example highly theoretical
example highly hypothetical example but
I personally have found that anal Devil
thinking is most useful for personal
problems personal issues in your life
okay all kinds of problems financial
partner work you know people say he all
that mean and it's always when you meet
the guy the other them he always I
talked quite softly but I'm the connect
person too
when someone gives me a suggestion in a
peaceful civilized way I'll always go to
me and say he yelled at me you know and
she said did he really okay so when you
have a challenge in your life pull this
out or else it has been useless or else
you are the devil's minion okay why
there's a tradition that if you come to
a class and you learn these things and
you don't use it you got worse it's okay
if you don't use it for somebody so use
it when you have personal challenges
this week try to get used to using it
and that's gonna be DC I love 11 like
how do you how do you get in the habit
bringing up angel devil song what do we
call it in countries where we're not
allowed to talk about angels and devils
we call it the tiger in the donkey okay
and we have a whole thing we have
puppets Tiger and donkey puppets
okay so in some countries where AC is
now we have rewritten the whole courses
and it takes training to deliver it
safely okay right you you and you John
did that Peter did that right you guys
helped me write it I think you know so
it takes some training to be safe okay
all right
[Music]
the 1:32 I still got four minutes don't
ask me how that minute passed failing to
bring up angel devil when you have
personal challenges will put this is
verse 132 the devil says will place you
and uniquely far away from an
understanding of emptiness I'll say it
again failing to use donkey Tiger
thinking ends up devil thinking when you
have a personal challenge in the next
few weeks you'll distance you from an
understanding of emptiness even further
okay failing to use it when you have it
creates a karma that you become more
emptiness stupid than you were before
okay that's depressing okay by the way
the opposite is also true
if you struggle to remember what we said
tonight when someone pisses you like
even if it's two days later it's a very
powerful bomb against the devil okay
even to remember two days later after
you not so upset and and you remember
what you were supposed to think
two days later it has a unique ability
to destroy the devil okay alright yeah
say chapter I should have said
okay I'll tell you kept oh I guess I had
a human dictionary I lived with the
human dictionary and I didn't know what
I just went upstairs with a cup of tea
because otherwise you couldn't get in
and asked him for tea
when it meant and here's his explanation
of chapter chapter is your kid acts up
and you built them this is too bad okay
you bailed them and then the next time
they just stick their but I'll just say
go for it you know and they get hardened
into it okay and test all means if you
don't remember that angel once it gets
harder the second time and then hard a
third time and you get more inured you
get more in order to not thinking about
the angel okay you get chap talk the
skin get callus I like that
that's kind of cool try to spell it I
don't know good luck
no temple it's got to be KH r EP or KH r
eb I think it's hard I think I've seen
it once in a book but it means you get
hardened to the indoor you get used to
not using it and then it gets worse okay
alright so we're stopped on 133 we're
gonna pick up on 134 and for the first
time I think we're gonna do a we're
gonna do something during the meditation
that's close that gets us a little
closer so it's the first time that the
devil says oh now that meditation it
wouldn't really hurt me but if you kept
doing it we'd have a problem so you know
so come back tomorrow or you will never
hear any kind of good meditation just
listen to it online
mr. Duncan can you do them $1
and again what do you think he Mary
Robinson and a camper sungazing
[Music]